Two major reservoirs, Lake Powell and
Mead, reach critically low levels.
Scientists are asking a new question,
what if we drain Lake Powell to save
Lake Mead?
>> This decision could impact the water
supply of about 40 million people,
including here in Utah. Samantha Hoffman
reports from Lake Powell.
>> As Lake Powell water levels near the
minimum threshold to generate
electricity through the dam, some
researchers question whether it may need
to change its function to best serve
communities.
>> Last year, literally in July, we were
boating around Lone Rock, um doing laps
around it. We were wakeboarding down
there.
>> Lake Powell is only 23% full, and it's
hard not to notice.
>> Now, I mean, you can clearly see you
can't even get to it without hiking over
there.
>> You'll hear these stories all throughout
the reservoir, from previously hidden
islands
>> Two and a half years ago when I moved
down here,
that wasn't visible.
>> to the stark bathtub ring.
>> When Lake Powell was full, the reservoir
reached all the way up to
that stark line.
>> Program director Zena Stats with the
Glen Canyon Institute studies what these
changing levels mean for the Glen Canyon
Dam.
>> Right now, we are at elevation 3527,
so 27 ft above the level that the Bureau
of Reclamation has identified as the
lowest possible level that they ever
want to let Glen Canyon Dam get to.
>> The past few months, the Bureau of
Reclamation has added emergency
solutions to keep above this minimum
level, known as de facto dead pool, so
the dam can still function. They've
reduced the amount of annual water that
can go through the dam through September
and began to add water from the Flaming
Gorge Reservoir through next April. With
these actions, the Bureau of Reclamation
projects they can keep Lake Powell at or
above the 3500 ft threshold through
April of 2027. But Stats calls this a
one-year band-aid solution.
>> We can't keep doing this. And if we have
the courage to take a step back and
think about, okay, why was Glen Canyon
Dam built?
Is that still working? The answer is no.
The dam was built from 1956 to 1963. It
was established by Congress and helped
upper Colorado River Basin states meet
the water delivery needs of lower Basin
states. Since about 2000, we've seen the
flows in this river diminish by an
average of 20%. There is less water than
was ever taken into consideration when
the designers and the engineers of this
dam were planning and constructing it.
>> Lake Mead created by the Hoover Dam is
down stream from the Glen Canyon Dam and
Lake Powell. It supplies water to major
cities in the lower Basin including Los
Angeles, Phoenix, and Las Vegas. But
like Lake Powell, it's only about a
quarter full.
>> I think it's worth asking the question.
We have the two largest reservoirs in
the country and we can't fill either
one. What might it look like if we were
to take the water that is currently
stored in Lake Powell, send it down
stream through the Grand Canyon, and
instead store it in Lake Mead?
>> the water flow through, such as they
could drill tunnels around the base of
the dam.
>> The Colorado River would be free flowing
through what is now Lake Powell. You
could keep the dam in place in order to
act as emergency water storage if Lake
Mead were ever to hit a point where it
could completely fill again.
>> No matter what the path forward is, many
agree a decision must be made soon
understanding the inarguably lowering of
water levels.
>> Coming over here and seeing it still
this low it's kind of
is definitely sad. It's definitely
shocking.
>> Whatever decisions get made, I hope that
they can kind of reflect the reality of
the situation we're in as opposed to the
desires that were possible in the past.
>> In Lake Powell, Smith and Hoffman, KUTV
2 News.